American Scholar Records
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
American Scholar Records 1926-2006 (bulk 1944-2005)
MSS46987
American Scholar
140,500 items 428 containers 171.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
A quarterly magazine of public affairs and culture published by the Phi Beta Kappa Society. Correspondence, business and editorial records, original manuscripts and edited drafts of works published by the Society in the American Scholar.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Bakeless, John, 1894-1978--Correspondence.; Barzun, Jacques, 1907-2012--Correspondence.; Bates, Marston, 1906-1974--Correspondence.; Benedict, Ruth, 1887-1948--Correspondence.; Brinton, Crane, 1898-1968--Correspondence.; Brooks, Van Wyck, 1886-1963--Correspondence.; Chase, Harry Woodburn, 1883-1955--Correspondence.; Commager, Henry Steele, 1902-1998--Correspondence.; Comstock, Ada Louise--Correspondence.; Davis, Elmer Holmes, 1890-1958--Correspondence.; Douglas, Paul H. (Paul Howard), 1892-1976--Correspondence.; Duffus, R. L. (Robert Luther), 1888- --Correspondence.; Edman, Irwin, 1896-1954--Correspondence.; Epstein, Joseph, 1937- --Correspondence.; Erskine, John, 1879-1951--Correspondence.; Finley, John H. (John Huston), 1863-1940--Correspondence.; Ford, Guy Stanton, 1873-1962--Correspondence.; Frank, Jerome, 1889-1957--Correspondence.; Gauss, Christian Frederick, 1878-1951--Correspondence.; Gellhorn, Walter, 1906- --Correspondence.; Gregg, Alan, 1890-1957--Correspondence.; Hamilton, Walton Hale, 1881-1958--Correspondence.; Haydn, Hiram Collins, 1907-1973--Correspondence.; Hazlitt, Henry, 1894-1993--Correspondence.; Hofstadter, Richard, 1916-1970--Correspondence.; Howe, Will David, 1873-1946--Correspondence.; Jarrell, Randall, 1914-1965--Correspondence.; Johnson, Alvin Saunders, 1874- --Correspondence.; Jones, Adam Leroy, 1873-1934--Correspondence.; Kronenberger, Louis, 1904-1980--Correspondence.; Krutch, Joseph Wood, 1893-1970--Correspondence.; Landis, James McCauley, 1899-1964--Correspondence.; Lerner, Max, 1902-1992--Correspondence.; Livingston, Burton E. (Burton Edward), 1875-1948--Correspondence.; Locke, Alain, 1885-1954--Correspondence.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982--Correspondence.; Malone, Dumas, 1892-1986--Correspondence.; Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978--Correspondence.; Miller, Perry, 1905-1963--Correspondence.; Moe, Henry Allen, 1894-1975--Correspondence.; Morley, Felix, 1894- --Correspondence.; Nason, John W.--Correspondence.; Neilson, William Allan, 1869-1946--Correspondence.; Nicholson, Marjorie Hope--Correspondence.; Niebuhr, Reinhold, 1892-1971--Correspondence.; Overstreet, H. A. (Harry Allen), 1875-1970--Correspondence.; Randall, John Herman, 1899-1980--Correspondence.; Redding, J. Saunders (Jay Saunders), 1906-1988--Correspondence.; Riesman, David, 1909-2002--Correspondence.; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976--Correspondence.; Schlesinger, Arthur M. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007--Correspondence.; Sears, Paul B. (Paul Bigelow), 1891-1990--Correspondence.; Shapley, Harlow, 1885-1972--Correspondence.; Shimer, William A. (William Allison), 1894- --Correspondence.; Simkhovitch, Mary K. (Mary Kingsbury), 1867-1951--Correspondence.; Stauffer, Donald A. (Donald Alfred), 1902-1952--Correspondence.; Van Doren, Irita Taylor, 1891-1966--Correspondence.; Welles, Sumner, 1892-1961--Correspondence.; Whicher, George Frisbie, 1889-1954--Correspondence.; Woodbridge, Frederick James Eugene, 1867-1940--Correspondence.
Organizations
Phi Beta Kappa.
Subjects
American literature--Periodicals.; American literature.; American periodicals.; Civilization--Periodicals.; Civilization.; Culture--Periodicals.; Culture.; History--Periodicals.; History.; Intellectual life--Periodicals.; Intellectual life.; Literature--Periodicals.; Literature.; Periodical editors--United States.; Political science--Periodicals.; Political science.; Politics, Practical--Periodicals.; Politics, Practical.; Religion--Periodicals.; Religion.; Science--Periodicals.; Science.
Titles
American Scholar.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Part I of the records of the American Scholar was given to the Library of Congress in 1966 by the United Chapters of Phi Beta Kappa. Additions to Part I were received from the same organization in 1971, 1975, 1978, and 1982. Part II of the records was given by the United Chapters of Phi Beta Kappa in 1987, 1992, and 1993. Part III of the records was given by the Phi Beta Kappa Society in 2002 and 2008.
Additional Guides
A list of American Scholar editorial staff and board members and selected indexes of correspondents in the General Editorial File and Author File of Part I, Accession No. 13,595 are available for use in the Manuscript Division Reading Room.
Transfers
Some photographs have been transferred to the Library's Prints and Photographs Division of the Library where they are identified as part of these papers.
Related Material
Related collections in the Manuscript Division include the records of
Phi Beta Kappa
.
Access and Restrictions
The records of the American Scholar are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Online Content
The American Scholar Web site http://www.theamericanscholar.org/ provides an archive of publications and a searchable database of authors, articles, and keywords useful in locating related material in these records.
Magazine History
Date Event
1932 Founded by the Phi Beta Kappa Society, New York, N.Y.
1932-1943 William Allison Shimer, editor
1943-1944 Marjorie Hope Nicolson, interim editor
1944-1973 Hiram Haydn, editor
1951 Editorial office moved to Williamsburg, Va.
1954 Editorial office moved to Washington, D.C.
1973-1997 Joseph Epstein, editor
1997-2004 Anne Fadiman, editor
2004- Robert Wilson, editor
Scope and Content Note
The American Scholar is a quarterly magazine of public affairs, literature, science, history, and culture published by the Phi Beta Kappa Society since 1932. Its records span the years 1926-2006, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period between 1944 and 2005. The collection is arranged in three parts.
While the American Scholar is anchored in the academic world, it is produced for a public audience and modeled on the call for independent thinking and interaction with the world as expressed in Ralph Waldo Emerson's Harvard College speech in 1837 of the same name. The editors of the publication built the magazine around a core of polished essays and wide-ranging book reviews. The volumes include poetry and, since 2006, fiction, along with varying departments, such as an editor's column, writer's journals, or thematic gleanings designated as “Commonplace Book.” Publication of reader replies has been a constant throughout its history.
Part I
The records of Part I of the American Scholar span the years 1926-1980, with the bulk of the material concentrated in the period between 1944 and 1976. It is arranged by accession number in the order in which it was received by the Library and thereunder as General Editorial File, Author File, or Miscellany.
The General Editorial File documents the daily activities of publishing the quarterly magazine. The correspondence reveals the relationship between the editor and his staff, especially after the editorial office moved to Williamsburg, Virginia, while the editor remained in New York. The routine tasks involved in printing, advertising, and distributing the magazine are also detailed. A significant aspect of this series is the correspondence between the editor and the members of the editorial board who were recognized authorities in a variety of fields.
The Author File contains correspondence with authors who submitted material to the magazine. It is possible to follow the progress of a manuscript from original submission through publication and the file includes comments by editorial board members, revisions or suggestions for revision, and requests for reprints. Very few of the actual manuscripts remain in the files; they were apparently returned to the author after publication or rejection.
Part II
Part II of the records of the American Scholar spans the years 1931-1988, with the bulk concentrated in the period 1976-1988. It is arranged in General Editorial File, Author File, and Miscellany series.
The earliest correspondence and financial reports in the General Editorial File pertain to the launching of the magazine and its formative years. Most of the later correspondence concerns regular features such as "The Revolving Bookstand," a book review column, and "The Reader Replies," a column for subscribers' responses to articles and occasionally rebuttals from the authors.
The Author File contains correspondence with authors who submitted articles for publication, including those authors who were rejected. In addition, the editor frequently solicited articles from well-known scholars. There is some overlap between the General Editorial File and the Author File because many writers who contributed regularly to standing departments of the magazine also submitted feature articles. Some of the correspondence pertains to copyright transfers and reprint permissions.
The Miscellany series primarily consists of correspondence soliciting poetry for publication. Included are Japanese sketches presented to Hiram Haydn as a Christmas greeting in 1957.
Part III
Part III of the records of the American Scholar spans the years 1984-2006, with the bulk concentrated in the period 1984-2005. It is arranged in Correspondence and Production File series.
The Correspondence File principally documents administrative matters of publication and includes exchanges between editors and staff and the authors of articles, book reviews, poetry, and other regular departments of the magazine. The series also includes correspondence from readers and subscribers as well as business files on printing, binding, advertising, and promotion. Alphabetical lists of authors prepared by American Scholar staff are included for files dated 2000-2006.
The Production File documents the editorial work of the magazine and includes original manuscripts, edited drafts, corrected galleys, as well as editorial correspondence with authors and between the staff who worked from afar at separate locations while communicating heavily by email and fax, with print copies preserved in the files. The editorial process during this phase of publication is described by Anne Fadiman in her final 2004 “Letter from the Editor,” as pouring each piece through a “series of increasingly fine-gauged sieves.”
Records for volumes dated 1984-1997 were arranged by American Scholar staff as “Original Manuscripts” and “Author's Galleys.” The revised arrangement of records for volumes dated 1998-2005 reflects the organization of the magazine during this later period. The American Scholar published works by noted authors, academic stars, Nobel Laureates, as well as new and otherwise obscure writers. Indexes printed in the Autumn issue of each volume facilitates location of specific works. The American Scholar Website http://www.theamericanscholar.org/ provides a searchable database of authors, articles, and keywords useful in locating related material in these records.
Arrangement of the Papers
The collection is arranged in three parts containing seventeen series:
Part I:
Accession No. 13,595, General Editorial File, 1932-1957
Accession No. 13,595, Miscellaneous, 1957-1960
Accession No. 13,595, Author File, circa 1930s-1957
Accession No. 15,221, General Editorial File, 1957-1960
Accession No. 15,221, Author File, 1957-1960
Accession No. 15,221, Miscellaneous, 1926-1965
Accession No. 16,509, Author File, 1960-1970
Accession No. 16,509, General Editorial File, 1951-1970
Accession No. 17,500, General Editorial File, 1965-1972
Accession No. 17,500, Author File, 1970-1973
Accession No. 18,559, General Editorial File, 1933-1980
Accession No. 18,559, Author File, 1973-1976
Part II:
General Editorial File, 1931-1988
Author File, 1932-1988
Miscellany, 1957-1986
Part III:
Correspondence, 1988-2006
Production File, 1984-2006
http://lccn.loc.gov/mm78046987
Container List
- Part I: Accession No. 13,595, General Editorial File, 1932-1957 (Box I:30)
  Correspondence, memoranda, and other items pertaining to the operations of publishing the American Scholar, its policies, organization, and relationships with advertising representatives, editorial board, Phi Beta Kappa, and printers. Includes editorial correspondence with authors contributing to continuing departments of the magazine, such as editorials and book reviews.
  Arranged chronologically by fiscal year (Aug-July) and therein by subject. An appendix of select correspondents in the file is available in the Manuscript Division Reading Room.
  - 1932-1945 (Box I:1)
    - Advertising
    - Circulation
      - General
      - Analysis
    - Editorial
      - Advisers
      - Board
      - Correspondence
        - Board
        - General
      - Readers' comments
      - General reprint permission
    - Printing and production
    - Promotion and publicity
      - Readers' Council
      - Promotion (Box I:2)
  - 1945-1947
    - Advertising
      - By American Scholar
      - James, William and Eleanor
      - Miscellaneous
    - American Scholar Series
    - Circulation
      - Bookstores
      - Renewal figures
    - Editorial
      - Advisers
      - Board
        - General
        - Members
          - Barzun, Jacques
          - Brooks, Van Wyck
          - Commager, Henry Steele
          - Duffus, Robert L.
          - Edman, Irwin (Box I:3)
          - Frank, Jerome
          - Gauss, Christian
          - Howe, Will D.
          - Lerner, Max
          - Nason, John W.
          - Nielson, William A.
          - Nicolson, Marjorie Hope
          - Robeson, Paul
          - Shapley, Harlow
          - Stauffer, Donald
          - Van Doren, Irita
          - Welles, Sumner
          - Whicher, George Frisbie
      - "American Scholar Forum"
        - Autumn 1946
        - Winter 1946-1947
        - Spring 1947
        - Summer 1947
      - General correspondence
        - Miscellaneous
          - A-F
          - G-Z, (2 folders) (Box I:4)
        - Wells, Carleton F.
      - Haydn, Hiram, personal file
      - Readers' Forum
        - Winter 1946-1947
        - Spring 1947
      - "The Reader Replies," summer 1947
    - Printing and production (Box I:5)
      - Rumford Press
        - Correspondence
        - Printing estimates
    - Promotion
      - Correspondence
      - General
      - Press releases
      - Special mailings, 1946-1947
        - Survey
        - Einstein, Albert
      - Publicity
  - 1947-1948
    - Advertising, William and Eleanor James
    - Circulation, bookstores
    - Editorial
      - Advisers
      - Board members (Box I:6)
        - Barzun, Jacques
        - Brooks, Van Wyck
        - Duffus, Robert L.
        - Edman, Irwin
        - Frank, Jerome
        - Gauss, Christian
        - Hamilton, Walton E.
        - Lerner, Max
        - Nicolson, Marjorie Hope
        - Niebuhr, Reinhold
        - Robeson, Paul
        - Shapley, Harlow
        - Stauffer, Donald
        - Van Doren, Irita
        - Whicher, George Frisbie
      - "American Scholar Forum"
        - Autumn 1947
        - Winter 1947-1948
        - Spring 1948
        - Summer 1948
      - General correspondence, (3 folders)
      - Haydn, Hiram, personal file (Box I:7)
        - Editors' of other magazines comments on fifteenth anniversary issue, autumn 1947
        - "The Reader Replies"
          - Autumn 1947
          - Winter 1947-1948
          - Spring 1948
          - Summer 1948
          - Miscellaneous, Oct. 1947-Aug. 1948
      - Printing and production
        - Binding
        - Rumford Press
        - Syndication agreements
        - William Byrd Press (Box I:8)
      - Promotion
        - Correspondence
        - Press releases
        - Special mailings
        - Single-copy mailing
        - Publicity
        - New member
        - Renewal figures
  - 1948-1949
    - Advertising
      - James, William and Eleanor
      - Miscellaneous
    - Circulation, bookstores
    - Editorial
      - Board
        - Elections
        - Meetings
        - Members
          - Barzun, Jacques
          - Brooks, Van Wyck
          - Duffus, Robert L.
          - Edman, Irwin
          - Frank, Jerome
          - Gauss, Christian
          - Hamilton, Walton (Box I:9)
          - Lerner, Max
          - Locke, Alain
          - Nicolson, Marjorie Hope
          - Niebuhr, Reinhold
          - Schlesinger, Arthur M., (1917-2007)
          - Shapley, Harlow
          - Stauffer, Donald
          - Van Doren, Irita
      - Editorials, Ralph Waldo Emerson, Secundus
      - "American Scholar Forum"
        - Autumn 1948
        - Winter 1948-1949
        - Spring 1949
        - Summer 1949
      - General correspondence, (2 folders)
      - Haydn, Hiram, personal file (Box I:10)
        - Portraits
          - Hand, Learned
          - DuBois, W. E. B.
      - "The Reader Replies"
        - Autumn 1948
        - Winter 1948-1949
        - Spring 1949
        - Summer 1949
        - Miscellaneous, 1948-1949
    - Printing and production
      - William Byrd Press
      - Correspondence
    - Promotion (Box I:11)
      - Correspondence
      - Press releases
      - Special mailings
        - Gauss, Christian, 1948
        - General
      - Direct mail
      - New members
      - Clippings
  - 1949-1950
    - Advertising
      - James, William and Eleanor
      - Miscellaneous
    - Circulation
      - Analysis
      - Bookstores
    - Editorial
      - Board
        - Elections
        - Meetings
        - Members
          - Edman, Irwin
          - Ford, Guy Stanton
      - Editorials, Ralph Waldo Emerson, Secundus
      - "American Scholar Forum"
        - Autumn 1949
        - Winter 1949-1950 (Box I:12)
        - Spring 1950
      - General correspondence, (2 folders)
      - Haydn, Hiram, personal file
        - Portraits
          - Bailey, Liberty Hyde
          - Henderson, Archibald
          - Schweitzer, Albert
      - "The Reader Replies"
        - Autumn 1949
        - Winter 1949-1950
        - Spring 1950
        - Summer 1950
        - Miscellaneous, 1949-1950 (Box I:13)
    - Printing and production
      - William Byrd Press
      - Correspondence
    - Promotion
      - Correspondence
      - Press releases
      - Special mailings
      - Direct mail
      - Publicity
  - 1950-1951
    - Advertising
      - James, William and Eleanor
      - Miscellaneous
    - Circulation, bookstores
    - Editorial
      - Board
        - Elections
        - Meetings
        - Members
          - Barzun, Jacques
          - Brooks, Van Wyck
          - Edman, Irwin
          - Ford, Guy Stanton
          - Gauss, Christian
          - Gregg, Alan
          - Hamilton, Walton
          - Schlesinger, Arthur M., (1917-2007) (Box I:14)
      - Editorials
      - "American Scholar Forum"
        - Autumn 1950
        - Winter 1950-1951
        - Spring 1951
        - Summer 1951
      - General
      - Haydn, Hiram, personal file
        - Portraits, Liberty Hyde Bailey
      - "The Reader Replies"
        - Winter, 1950-1951
        - Spring 1951 (Box I:15)
        - Summer 1951
        - Miscellaneous, 1950-1951
      - "The Revolving Bookstand"
        - Committee
        - Publishers
        - Reviewers
          - Spring 1951
          - Summer 1951
    - Printing and production
      - Syndication agreements
      - William Byrd Press
    - Promotion
      - Correspondence
      - Press releases
      - Special mailings
    - Advertising
      - By American Scholar
      - James, William and Eleanor
    - Circulation, bookstores (Box I:16)
    - Editorial
      - Board
        - Elections
        - Meetings
        - Members
          - Brinton, Crane
          - Brooks, Van Wyck
          - Edman, Irwin
          - Ford, Guy Stanton
          - Gauss, Christian
          - Gellhorn, Walter
          - Locke, Alain
          - Moe, Henry Allen
          - Redding, J. Saunders
          - Schlesinger, Arthur M., (1917-2007)
          - Sears, Paul B.
          - Shapley, Harlow
          - Van Doren, Irita
      - Editorials
      - "American Scholar Forum"
        - Autumn 1951
        - Winter 1951-1952
        - Spring 1952
        - Summer 1952
        - General
        - General
      - Haydn, Hiram
        - Phi Beta Kappa
        - American Scholar
      - Manuscripts received (Box I:17)
      - Portraits, Christian Gauss
      - "The Reader Replies"
        - Autumn 1951
        - Winter 1951-1952
        - Spring 1952
        - Summer 1952
        - Miscellaneous, 1951-1952
      - "The Revolving Bookstand"
        - Committee
        - Publishers
        - Reviewers
          - Autumn 1951
          - Winter 1951-1952
          - Spring 1952
          - Summer 1952
    - Printing and production (Box I:18)
      - William Byrd Press
      - Hodes-Daniel Co.
    - Promotion
      - Correspondence
      - Press releases
      - Special mailings
  - 1952-1953
    - Advertising, William and Eleanor James
    - Circulation
      - Bookstores
      - Request for American Scholar list
    - Editorial
      - Board
        - Elections
        - Meetings
        - Members (Box I:19)
      - Editorials
      - "American Scholar Forum," autumn 1952
      - General
      - Haydn, Hiram
        - Personal file
        - Phi Beta Kappa
        - American Scholar, Aug. 1952-July 1953, (2 folders)
      - Manuscripts received
      - "The Reader Replies"
        - Autumn 1952
        - Winter 1952-1953
        - Spring 1953
        - Summer 1953
        - Miscellaneous, 1952-1953, (2 folders)
      - "The Revolving Bookstand" (Box I:20)
        - Committee
        - Publishers
          - General
          - University presses
        - Reviewers
          - Autumn 1952
          - Winter 1952-1953
          - Spring 1953
          - Summer 1953
          - Miscellaneous, 1952-1953
      - Printing and production
        - William Byrd Press
        - Hodes-Daniel Co.
      - Promotion
        - Correspondence
        - Press releases (Box I:21)
        - Special mailings
  - 1953-1954
    - Advertising, William and Eleanor James
    - Circulation, request for American Scholar list
    - Editorial
      - Board
        - Elections
        - Meetings
        - Members
      - "American Scholar Forum"
        - Autumn 1953
        - Spring 1954
      - General
      - Haydn, Hiram
        - Personal file
          - Phi Beta Kappa
          - American Scholar (Box I:22)
      - Manuscripts received
      - "The Reader Replies"
        - Autumn 1953
        - Winter 1953-1954
        - Summer 1954
        - Miscellaneous, 1953-1954
      - "The Revolving Bookstand"
        - Committee
        - Publishers, (2 folders)
        - Reviewers
          - Autumn 1953
          - Winter 1953-1954
          - Spring 1954
          - Summer 1954 (Box I:23)
          - Miscellaneous, 1953-1954
    - Printing and production, William Byrd Press
    - Promotion
      - Correspondence
      - Press releases
  - 1954-1955
    - Advertising, William and Eleanor James
    - Circulation, bookstores
    - Editorial
      - Board
        - Meetings
        - Members
      - Foundations investigation
      - General
      - Haydn, Hiram (Box I:24)
        - Personal file
        - Phi Beta Kappa
        - American Scholar
      - Manuscripts received
      - Personnel